<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: seo | Hackers Gonna Hack]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/categories/seo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.jeffknupp.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-10T06:02:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.jeffknupp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Knupp]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Single Founder SEO: Building Your Personal Brand]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/29/single-founder-seo-building-your-personal-brand/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-29T06:10:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/29/single-founder-seo-building-your-personal-brand</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a single founder, I realize I am at a tremendous disadvantage when it comes to non-technical work. There are only so many hours in a day, and I have a full-time job. Work on <a href="http://www.linkrdr.com">linkrdr</a>, therefore, must be prioritized. With so many interesting technical challenges to solve, a number of other useful activities fall by the wayside. Marketing is a big one. So how do I focus my efforts? <strong>By building my personal brand.</strong></p>

<!--more-->


<p>In a perfect world, I'd be part of a multi-person team working on the site full-time. A large portion of <em>someone's</em> time would be devoted to getting the word out about linkrdr, improving the copy on our pages, and making sure we were doing everything right when it came to converting users. Since I can't devote a ton of time to those activities without sacrificing the core experience of linkrdr, I have to be smart about how I <em>do</em> spend my time marketing.</p>

<p>As it turns out, I do very little real "marketing" for the site.  Instead, I'm focused on a slightly different strategy which, I hope, will pay dividends in the long run regardless of whether or not linkrdr is a success. <em>I'm building my personal brand.</em> Though it may sound slimy or silly, it's really just the process by which you get your name "out there" and attached to things that people find useful.</p>

<p>For me, one obvious way to build my brand is through this blog. Don't misunderstand: the blog was not started as a way to drive traffic anywhere. Rather, I started the blog because I felt that I had <em>taken</em> more from the technology community than I had <em>given</em>. It was my way of giving back.  That said, it has turned out to be a rather good tool for generating traffic, though not directly. The most traffic linkrdr has received was through others finding my blog and posting about it. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Winer">Dave Winer</a> found the blog through a Hacker News post which with I had nothing to do. Between the Hacker News post and his Tweet of linkrdr, 700 users signed up in one day. Even though I didn't cause this directly, I had positioned myself well for something like this to happen.</p>

<p>When I blog about programming related topics, I'll usually post them to proggit or Hacker News, depending on the content. I'm not spamming every day with off-topic content (I hope). I'm just letting people know, "Hey, I wrote about this technical topic you might find interesting". Like all things, some posts take off and drive thousands of visitors to the site while others are merely blips on the radar. With every post, though, I'm reaching more people. The more people I reach, the more chance I have of reaching <em>influencers</em>.</p>

<p>A word of advice: do not start a <em>personal</em> blog simply to drive traffic somewhere else. Most times, it will be transparent and turn people off. Remember, your name is attached to this, for better or worse. On the other hand, it's quite customary to build a blog for your site overflowing with link-bait content. I think for the most part this is accepted practice now, though I choose to reserve the blog space on linkrdr for messages to users.</p>

<p>While blogging is a fantastic way to build your personal brand, it is certainly not the only way. Becoming active on StackOverflow serves two purposes: you get a chance to give back to the technology community at large and you begin to establish yourself as a domain expert (hopefully). I've found contributing to Stack Overflow to be rewarding even though it doesn't directly drive traffic to the site. At the very least it's another part of your personal portfolio that establishes your technical credibility.</p>

<p>Contributing to open source projects or creating your own is similarly helpful. <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com">Patrick McKenzie</a>, whom Hacker News readers probably better recognize as <strong>patio11</strong>, created a dialogue with other developers in creating A/Bingo, the Ruby A/B testing software grown from his BingoCardCreator site. Probably the best <em>recent</em> example of personal brand building, Patrick went from Japanese salary-man to self-sufficient entrepreneur through a (seemingly, but not definitely) long, targeted campaign at getting his name out there. It worked, and he now consults professionally in addition to running a number of websites.  Open source software starts the conversation with others. Especially if your project is technology related, throwing it on GitHub can rarely hurt.</p>

<p>One side note: on all the sites I contribute to, I do so under the same username, jknupp. This is done purposely. What good is building your personal brand when you're doing it as NinjaPirate14? Use your real name or some variation thereof. It will have the adding benefit of stopping you from submitting something you wouldn't want your name attached to, which probably shouldn't be posted in the first place.</p>

<p>linkrdr is still in its infancy, having only begun two and a half weeks ago, but it already has a good number of users. Almost all of them found the site through finding <em>me</em>. Building your brand as a single founder may be the most time effective form of SEO available. It's certainly a good thing to do regardless, as you never know where opportunities will come from.</p>

<p>Questions or comments on <em>Single Founder SEO: Bulding Your Personal Brand</em>? Let me know below or email me at <a href="mailto:jknupp@gmail.com">jknupp@gmail.com</a>. Also, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/jeffknupp/">follow me on Twitter</a> to see all of my blog posts and updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How linkrdr went semi-viral]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/21/how-linkrdr-went-semi-viral/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-21T04:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/21/how-linkrdr-went-semi-viral</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was a bit under the weather this past weekend, but it turns out I
wasn't the only thing to go viral. Below is a brief story of how <a href="http://www.linkrdr.com">linkrdr</a> enjoyed it's first encouter with virality.</p>

<h2>Background</h2>

<p>Before Saturday, linkrdr had about 10 users, who had figured out a way
to signup without me really providing one. Sometime Thursday evening, I
believe, I slapped a 'Beta' sticker on the front page, cleaned some
stuff up, and declared linkrdr open for business. Come the weekend, I
was under the weather and not feeling like working on anything, so I
didn't check any of my sites until Monday at 4pm. I cruised over to my
<a href="http://getclicky.com/66528953">Clicky</a> dashboard and took a look at the
stats for this blog. Then something caught my eye...</p>

<p><img src="http://66.228.46.113/static/img/linkrdr_growth.png" title="linkrdr visits per day" ></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>"Uh oh"</h2>

<p>The graph for linkrdr, which is usually totally flat, had suddenly
shot up almost vertically. I quickly checked the number of users via the
django console and felt a pit in my stomach: <strong>720 users had signed up
in the past 24 hours</strong>. I caught my breath, then checked how many total
links linkrdr was managing. I read the number three times. I couldn't
believe it: <strong>109,214 links</strong> across about 3,700 feeds. I fired up my
browser to see if the site had melted down. To my surprise, it was
pretty responsive. After clicking around more and convincing myself the
server wasn't on fire, I did a little <a href="http://getclicky.com/66528953">Clicky</a> style investigating.</p>

<p>It became clear rather quickly that most of my links were coming from
two sources: <a href="http://www.startupsea.com">startupsea.com</a>, a new
startup-roundup type site I hadn't heard of, and
<a href="http://www.scripting.com">scripting.com</a>. When I saw the second site,
my heart skipped a beat. I'm very familiar with scripting.com, the blog
of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Winer">Dave Winer</a>. I checked out
scripting.com and sitting there on his list of links was a link to
linkrdr. He had also tweeted about it to his <strong>75,000</strong> followers.
Between the two sites, linkrdr had gone mini-viral.</p>

<h2>Aftermath</h2>

<p>I quickly decided that I needed to bullet-proof the site (how I did so
will be the topic of my next post). I was proud
that the site could handle the drastic uptick in flow, but I wasn't
going to leave anything to chance. Over the past 18 hours, I've been
adding features that users have been clamoring for (OPML import has been
added, for one), fixing bugs, and generally cleaning things up. It's still too early to
tell if this was just a one-off blip, as the US public had Monday off of
work. Tuesday morning will be an interesting one. Let's hope linkrdr
gets more viral-love!</p>

<p>Questions or comments on <em>How linkrdr Went Semi-Viral</em>? Let me know in the comments below. Also, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/jeffknupp">follow me on Twitter</a> to see all of my blog posts and updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Analytics for Django Sites]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/07/analytics-for-django-sites/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-07T22:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/07/analytics-for-django-sites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first in a series of posts I plan to do over the next month about Analytics and Django. In this post I'll walk through how I began to use a number of analytics tools to
drive decisions about my site, <a href="http://www.illestrhyme.com">IllestRhyme</a>.</p>

<p>One of the first things I did when writing
<a href="http://www.illestrhyme.com">IllestRhyme</a> was to sign up for Google
Analytics. I had never run a web site before, but I was aware of
Google's analytics offering. I admit, for the first few weeks after the
site went live I would start at the Google Analytics page and <strong>hope</strong> to
see users in the Live View. I wasn't really using the data for anything.
I was using Google Analytics as a virtual scoreboard.</p>

<p>It wasn't until I signed up for <a href="http://getclicky.com/66528953">Clicky</a>
that I started to take analytics seriously. In fact, more specifically,
it was when I combined Clicky and
<a href="https://github.com/jcassee/django-analytical">django-analytical</a> that I
really took my first deep-dive into using analytical data for decision
making. Since django-analytical already integrates with a number of
analytics services, including Clicky, setup was a breeze. Sure, I could
have inserted the raw code into my Django templates, but
django-analytical gave me a single point at which to configure all my
analytics services.</p>

<p>More importantly, and I can not stress this enough,
<strong>django-analytical's Clicky integration let me see my users in Clicky via
their contrib.auth usernames</strong>. This was <strong>huge</strong>. Now, instead of
staring at IP addresses, I could follow users on their visit to the site (using
<a href="http://getclicky.com/66528953">Clicky's</a> awesome Spy feature) in
real-time by username. Believe me, nothing will teach you more about you
users than recognizing usernames and their associated behavior patterns.
I could tell which users were hitting the site to check quickly for
updates, which users hung around for a while, and which users <em>used the
site like it was crack</em>. It was this last group that I was initially
interested in.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I discovered I had about four or five <em>hardcore</em> users, that were on the
site for hours a day. Now, part of that is just personality, but in
addition, <em>something on the site clicked for them</em>. Since I want all my
users on the site for hours a day, I decided to determine what they were
doing in a more rigorous fashion. Naturally, I started coding...</p>

<p>I ended up writing a middleware that tracked a configurable set of users as
they browsed the site and stored this information in the database. I
then processed this information and organized it into "activities". If a
user was going through all the new rhymes submitted and voting on them,
this was 'updating'. If the user was submitting a bunch of new rhymes,
this was 'bulk submitting', etc. After analyzing this information for my
power users and a random sampling of other users, I noticed they were doing one thing more than any other,
which I didn't even have a category for: they were following each other.</p>

<p>This was strange to me, as I didn't think of IllestRhyme as a community.
To me it was more like a tool to get better at rapping. To some of my users, at least, it
was a destination; a way to interact with like-minded people. I quickly
realized the value of this and set to work adding tools that would
encourage this interaction.</p>

<p>Using
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/psam/django-postman/wiki/Home">django-postman</a> I
gave them the ability to send Private Messages. I encouraged commenting
by increasing the amount of Rep (virtual points representing a user's
'reputation' on the site, sort of like StackOverflow) adding comments
was worth. Voting on other users' verses also received a boost.</p>

<p>That's just one example of the ways I use the analytics data I collect
from <a href="http://getclicky.com/66528953">Clicky</a>, Google Analytics, HubSpot,
and the rest to make decisions about my site. In my next Analytics post,
I'll take a look at A/B testing in Django. Stay tuned!</p>

<p>Questions or comments on <em>Analytics for Django Sites</em>? Let me know in the comments below. Also, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/jeffknupp">follow me on Twitter</a> to see all of my blog posts and updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Responding Quickly To Customers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/06/on-responding-quickly-to-customers/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-06T03:18:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/06/on-responding-quickly-to-customers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I wrote my last post, which hit the frontpage of HackerNews, I
wanted to see what the HNers would see. So I cleared my cookies, logged
out, and navigated over to <a href="http://www.illestrhyme.com">IllestRhyme</a>.
When I got there, something caught my eye:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.illestrhyme.com:8080/images/chat.jpg"></p>

<p>It's normal for me to be talking to users, and normal for me to be
responding to requests from users. <strong>If this isn't normal for you, it should be</strong>.
Part of the reason IllestRhyme has a community feel is that the users
get the sense that their requests don't go off into the ether. I'm
hanging around, reading their emails, forum posts, and chat transcripts.
If they suggest something, I almost always implement it. What's more,
they are rewarded for their suggestion through Rep points, which tracks
reputation on the site.</p>

<p>I love the size of the site as it is right now. Sure, I want the number
of users to explode, but with about 150 users, I know all of them, talk
to them frequently, and have a general idea of the type of user they are
(power, casual, etc).</p>

<p><strong>The number of users on the site may go up, but my interaction with them
won't end.</strong> My first hire would ideally be a community rep. I can take
care of the programming and marketing, but I never want my users to feel
like they don't have my ear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advertising: Reddit versus Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/02/advertising-reddit-versus-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-02T05:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/02/02/advertising-reddit-versus-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To acquire users for <a href="http://www.illestrhyme.com">IllestRhyme</a>, a user content driven rap site I started, I ran two ads: one on Reddit and one on Facebook. The results were startling.</p>

<p>According to the data from <a href="http://getclicky.com/66528953">Clicky</a>, the analytics engine I use most, Reddit sent me roughly 170 visitors for a 3 day ad, purchased at $30 per day. Of those visitors, only 5 registered for the site. That gives me a conversion rate of 2.8%, at a cost of $18. I'm happy to eat the cost up front for new users as they're the lifeblood of the site, but $18 is pretty extreme.</p>

<p>After the Reddit ad ran its course, I created a Facebook ad with the same parameters: $30 a day, however many visitors that buys me. In the first 12 hours of the Facebook ad, I received 33 visitors, <em>9 of whom signed up</em>. Now I realize it's still a bit early to call the race, but even if I get no more visitors from the Facebook ad, my cost of acquisition was $10, 55% cheaper than for the Reddit ad. If my <em>27% conversion rate</em> keeps up, 170 visitors would net me 46 users, at a cost of only $1.96.</p>

<p>I realize this data isn't comprehensive, but it's still eye opening. Part of this can be attributed to the more focused targeting I was able to do through Facebook. Facebook let me specify that my ad only be shown to the 7 million or so users who:
1. Live in the US
2. Are 18 or older
3. like #Freestyle rap, #Hip hop music, or #Rapping</p>

<p>Conversely, on Reddit I was forced to choose a subreddit to advertise on (along with a small percentage of the site at large). I chose /r/hiphopheads as it's a large (by Reddit standards) and active subreddit.</p>

<p>Regardless of the targeting differences, I think it's safe to assume that Facebook users are at least more willing to sign up for websites than are Reddit users. Interestingly, I use the Facebook registration app for my registration form. It's not clear from the data (I'm running an A/B test now), but it appears that Facebook users are more willing to sign up if they are presented with a Facebook form to fill out. For Reddit users, who are more Internet savvy, this may actually be a deterrent.</p>

<p>Of course this doesn't take into account what <em>kind</em> of users those who registered will turn out to be. It may be the case that Facebook users are more likely to sign up for something and never use it (although the initial data indicates this isn't the case, at least categorically). Those five Reddit users may be the five most active users on IllestRhyme for the next year. For $18 a piece, they better be.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
